<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>devzen on Gliush Notebook</title>
    <link>https://gliush.github.io/categories/devzen/</link>
    <description>Recent content in devzen on Gliush Notebook</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 22 Feb 2020 17:25:05 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://gliush.github.io/categories/devzen/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Notes for episode-0276</title>
      <link>https://gliush.github.io/devzen_note/0276/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 22 Feb 2020 17:25:05 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gliush.github.io/devzen_note/0276/</guid>
      <description>Using Alpine can make Python Docker builds 50× slower https://pythonspeed.com/articles/alpine-docker-python/
 Стандартная рекомендация по созданию docker-образов - использовать alpine linux. Размер маленький, более быстрая сборка  Ubuntu собирает gcc за 30сек, образ весит 150МБ Alpine собирает gcc за 15сек, образ весит 105МБ   Сборка Python образа (matplotlib, pandas):  Ubuntu 30sec -&amp;gt; 363MB Alpine linux не работает с предкомпилированными библиотеками из-за glibc -&amp;gt; собирать из исходников -&amp;gt; 1557сек, 851МБ. Один из комментаторов добился 470МБ за счет multi-stage build   Дополнительные проблемы во время работы  Alpine имеет меньший размер стэка для потоков.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Notes for episode-0275</title>
      <link>https://gliush.github.io/devzen_note/0275/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Feb 2020 18:25:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gliush.github.io/devzen_note/0275/</guid>
      <description>The Influence of Organizational Structure on Software Quality: An Empirical Case Study https://www.cs.umd.edu/~basili/publications/proceedings/P125.pdf
 INTRODUCTION Software quality is obtain usually from:  code coverage code churn code complexity code dependencies   But not from &amp;ldquo;organizational structure&amp;rdquo; -&amp;gt; question they want to cover Conway&#39;s Law: &amp;ldquo;organizations that design systems are constrained to produce systems which are copies of the communication structures of these organizations Mythical Man Month: &amp;ldquo;the product quality is strongly affected by org structure&amp;rdquo; RELATED WORK - great section about different papers about the topic ORGANIZATIONAL METRICS  Number of Engineers (NOE), who touched the binary and is still in the company Number of Ex-Engineer (NOEE) Edit Frequency (EF) Depth of Master Ownership (DMO): level of the team who owns 75% of edits Percentage of Org contributing to the development (PO) Level of Organizational Code Ownership (OCO) Overall Organization Ownership (OOW) Organization Intersection Factor (OIF)   CASE STUDY &amp;amp; RESULTS  Windows Vista bugs &amp;amp; code change information (from VCS) 3404 binaries, &amp;gt; 50M LOC       </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Notes for episode-0274</title>
      <link>https://gliush.github.io/devzen_note/0274/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Feb 2020 15:55:47 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gliush.github.io/devzen_note/0274/</guid>
      <description>Language Bias in Accident Investigations http://lup.lub.lu.se/luur/download?func=downloadFile&amp;amp;recordOId=2971193&amp;amp;fileOId=2971195
 The paper examined the language and content of the U.S. Forest Service&#39;s Serios Accident Investigation Guide (SAIG) Idea: check if it biased the accident analysis process (tl;dr - yes) The Influence of Philosophy on Accident Investigation  The influence is large. Today&#39;s models are based on &amp;lsquo;cause-end-effect&amp;rsquo; reasoning They follow the need to create a logical pattern of &amp;lsquo;facts&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;conclusions&amp;rsquo; Even when the existence of a pattern is questionable   The evolution of Accident Models  Sequential accident model  WWI -&amp;gt; accidents in a munition factory.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>